Guide to the Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation Records, 1929-1993 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation records 1929-1993 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation
5.5 linear feet Extent: 4300 Items
The Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation was an outdoor advertising company that operated in northern Ohio from 1965 to 2000. The Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation Records span the years 1929 to 1993 and include clippings, corporation reports, negatives, photograph albums, photographs, poster boards, promotional materials, regional maps, slides, and trade literature that document the operational history of Ohio Outdoor and related companies. The bulk of this collection consists of photographs and slides of billboards in northern Ohio from 1937 to 1993. Also included are photographs of Ohio street locations and outdoor advertising activities. Other outdoor advertising companies represented in the collection reflect mergers, acquisitions, and business connections between Ohio Outdoor and other firms, and include Dingeman Advertising, Inc.; Outdoor Communications, Inc. (OCI); Outdoor Graphics, Inc.; Indiana Outdoor Advertising Corporation; Kentucky Outdoor Advertising Corporation; E.A. Eckert Advertising Company; and T.R. Sammons Outdoor Advertising Company.
RL.00970
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation Records were received by the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library as a gift in 1997; 2006.
Historical Note
Chronology List
1965 Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation was founded as a subsidiary of American Bakeries Company. The company was owned by Norman Knight and managed by Howard N. Johansen.
1971 Outdoor Graphics, Inc. founded as a subsidiary of American Bakeries Company
1978 Ohio Outdoor purchased by Howard Johansen
1988 Ownership of Ohio Outdoor transferred to Claire F. Johansen and Nancy L. Freeman, daughters of Howard Johansen
1989 Outdoor Communications, Inc. (OCI) acquired Dingeman Advertising, Inc. (a subsidiary of Ohio Outdoor)
1998 Lamar Advertising Company acquired OCI
2000 Lamar Advertising Company purchased Ohio Outdoor
During the 1970s, Indiana Outdoor Advertising Corporation and Kentucky Outdoor Advertising Corporation were founded.
Collection Overview
The Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation Records span the years 1929-1993 and include clippings, corporation reports, negatives, photographs, poster boards, promotional materials, regional maps, slides, and trade literature that document the operational history of Ohio Outdoor and related companies. The bulk of this collection consists of photographs and slides of billboards in northern Ohio from 1937-1993. Also included are photographs of Ohio street locations and outdoor advertising activities. Other outdoor advertising companies represented in the collection reflect mergers, acquisitions, and business connections between Ohio Outdoor and other firms, and include Dingeman Advertising, Inc.; Outdoor Communications, Inc. (OCI); Outdoor Graphics, Inc.; Indiana Outdoor Advertising Corporation; Kentucky Outdoor Advertising Corporation; E.A. Eckert Advertising Company; and T.R. Sammons Outdoor Advertising Company.
The collection is organized into two series: Business Files and Photographs, Negatives and Slides. The Business Files Series includes clippings, corporation reports, poster boards, promotional materials, and regional maps. Large regional maps and poster boards in this series were used for presentations. The Photographs, Negatives and Slides Series makes up the bulk of the collection, and chiefly consists of photographs and slides of billboards in northern Ohio from the 1930s-1990s. Photographs by the E.A. Eckhert Company also document Ohio street locations and outdoor advertising activties. Included are photographs of actress and Westinghouse spokeswoman Betty Furness and a 1938 photograph of a handmade sign in support of Adolph Hitler hanging over a billboard. Slides, which range from 1967-1978, were used in business presentations for outdoor advertising staff or to improve public relations through community outreach.
Large-format materials have been removed from their original series locations and relocated to Oversize Materials. Relocated items have been replaced in the Detailed Description of the Collection by dummy folders enclosed in brackets.
Subject Headings
Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation (Firm); Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation -- History; Lamar Advertising Company -- History; Outdoor Advertising Association of America; Advertising, Outdoor; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States -- History; Advertising, Outdoor -- Ohio; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies -- Ohio; Billboards -- United States; Billboards -- Ohio; Clippings; Corporation reports; Negatives; Photographs; Promotional materials; Slides (photographs); Regional maps; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Materials related to this collection may be found in other Hartman Center collections, including the Outdoor Advertising Association of America (OAAA) Archives, OAAA Poster Design Collection, and the OAAA Slide Library.
Contents of Collection
- Business Files Series, 1951-1991 and undated, (1 box)
  Consists of administrative records, clippings, corporation reports, lecture notes, trade literature, and promotional materials that document the organizational history of Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation and related companies. Includes a matted press release and photographic reproduction announcing the sale of outdoor advertising plants from Foster & Kleiser to Ohio Outdoor. Arranged alphabetically.
  Restrictions on access: Contains unsleeved photographs; gloves are required when handling.
  - American Display Systems, Inc. promotional booklet, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1983-1991 and undated (Box 1)
  - Community profiles, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - Corporation records, 1975-1985 and undated, (8 folders)
    - Draft corporation records, 1974-1979 and undated (Box 1)
    - Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation
      - Business plans, 1975-1976, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - Exhibits, 1975 (Box 1)
      - Rate schedules, 1977, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Outdoor Graphics, Inc.
      - Business Plans, 1975 (Box 1)
      - Exhibits, 1975 (Box 1)
  - [Foster & Kleiser matted press release, 1965, removed to Folder 1] (Box 1)
  - Lecture notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Ohio Outdoor files
    - [Draft regional maps, circa 1970s, removed to Oversize Materials Box 7] (Box 1)
    - [Maps and miscellaneous, circa 1970s, removed to Folder 1] (Box 1)
    - Operating territory maps, 1977 and undated (Box 1)
    - [Presentation boards, circa 1970s, removed to Oversize Materials Box 6] (Box 1)
    - Promotional materials, circa 1990s (Box 1)
    - [Regional presentation maps, circa 1970s, removed to Oversize Materials Box 7] (Box 1)
  - [Presentation boards, circa 1970s, removed to Oversize Materials Box 6] (Box 1)
  - Standard Outdoor Advertising, Inc. promotional booklet, circa 1950s (Box 1)
  - Trade literature, 1951-1990 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - [Miscellaneous maps and sign, circa 1970s, removed to Oversize Materials Box 6] (Box 1)
- Photographs, Negatives and Slides Series, 1929-1994 and undated, (5 Boxes)
  Consists of photographs, negatives, and slides that document billboards and the outdoor advertising industry in northern Ohio. Series is arranged into three categories: Loose photographs and negatives; Photograph albums; and Slides. The Loose photographs and negatives and Photograph albums categories share similar content. The bulk of photographs are of northern Ohio billboards from the 1970s-1990s that promoted both local and national products and services. The majority of outdoor advertising companies represented in this series were linked with Ohio Outdoor Advertising Company through business ties, with the exception of Hart Advertising, Inc., which was a rival to Ohio Outdoor. The earlier E.A. Eckhert photographs (1937-1970s) also include images of Ohio street locations and outdoor advertising activities. Included are photographs of actress and Westinghouse spokeswoman Betty Furness posing with members of the Advertising Club of North Central Ohio, and a 1938 photograph of a handmade sign in support of Adolph Hitler hanging over a billboard. Slides, which range from 1967-1978, were used in instructional presentations for outdoor advertising staff or to improve public relations through community outreach. Some slide sets in this collection were developed by the Outdoor Advertising Association of America (OAAA) and designed to be distributed to outdoor advertising companies across the United States for use in their local community presentations to city councils and the general public.
  - Loose photographs and negatives, 1929-1994 and undated
    Consists of black and white and color photographs and negatives. Arranged in alphabetical order within category, with the exception of the Hart photographs, which have been kept in original order.
    - Dingeman and OCI billboard photographs, 1983-1994 and undated (Box 1)
      - Automobiles, services and accessories, 1987-1990 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
      - Beer and wine, undated (Box 2)
      - Commercial services, undated (Box 2)
      - Education, 1989 and undated (Box 2)
      - Food, supermarkets and restaurants, 1983-1994 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Health and fitness, 1989 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Insurance and financial institutions, 1988 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Mass media, 1988 and undated (Box 3)
      - Non-profits and miscellaneous, 1985-1991 and undated (Box 3)
      - Political, 1989 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Residential and commercial products and services, 1988 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
      - Retail businesses, 1994 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Special events, 1990-1994 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Unrelated, undated (Box 4)
    - E.A. Eckhert Advertising Company photographs, 1929-1976 and undated
      - E.A. Eckhert billboards, 1942-1960 and undated (Box 4)
      - Other outdoor advertising company billboards, 1942-1976 and undated (Box 4)
      - Other photographs, 1947-1960 and undated (Box 4)
      - Street location photographs, undated 1959 and undated (Box 4)
      - T.R. Sammons billboards, 1929-1938 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Hart billboard photographs and negatives, 1978, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Ohio Outdoor billboard photographs, 1980 and undated (Box 4)
  - Photograph albums, circa 1940s-1993 and undated
    Consists of black and white and color photographs and negatives that were originally kept in photograph albums. Much of the content is similar to photographs in Loose photographs and negatives. Arranged in original order.
    - Computer Image Systems, Inc. photograph album, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
    - Dingeman and OCI photograph albums, 1982-1988 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - E.A. Eckhert photograph album, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 5)
    - [Indiana Outdoor photograph album, 1971, removed to Oversize Materials Box 8] (Box 5)
    - [Kentucky Outdoor photograph album, 1973, removed to Oversize Materials Box 8] (Box 5)
    - OCI best design contest photograph album, 1992 (Box 5)
    - [Ohio Outdoor photograph album, 1974, removed to Oversize Materials Box 8] (Box 5)
  - Slides, 1967-1978 and undated
    Consists of color slides that were used for presentations. Arranged in original order.
    - Basic Bulletin, circa mid-1970s (Box 5)
    - Billboards, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Billboards Painesville, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Freshen Up-Going Up, 1975-1978 and undated (Box 5)
    - Hart Boards, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Long handled posting and scrape, paint Elynia, cedar trim, 1974-1978 and undated (Box 5)
    - Naegele, 1967-1973 (Box 5)
    - OAAA materials
      - City Councils, 11a- Urban Ordinance Committee, circa 1970s (Box 5)
      - Urban Ordinance Kit, 1970s
        - City Council Presentation (Box 5)
        - General presentation, (2 folders) (Box 5)
        - No Outdoor in Europe: Rebuttal (Box 5)
    - OOAC good pics, 1968 (Box 5)
    - OOAC: How the Plant Should Not Look, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Urban Ordinance, circa mid-1970s (Box 5)
- Oversize Materials
  - Business Files Series, 1951-1991 and undated
    - Miscellaneous maps and sign, circa 1970s (Box 6)
    - Ohio Outdoor presentation boards, circa 1970s (Box 6)
    - Presentation boards, circa 1970s (Box 6)
    - Ohio Outdoor draft regional maps, circa 1970s, (3 folders) (Box 7)
      - Ashtabula through Fremont (Box 7)
      - Fremont-Tiffin through Norwalk (Box 7)
      - Norwalk-Bellevue through Tiffin (Box 7)
    - Ohio Outdoor regional presentation maps, circa 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Cleveland West through Fremont-Tiffin (Box 7)
      - Lorain through Toledo suburban (Box 7)
    - Foster & Kleiser matted press release, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Ohio Outdoor regional presentation maps, circa 1970s (Box 9)
  - Photographs, Negatives, and Slides Series, 1929-1994 and undated
    - Indiana Outdoor photograph album, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Kentucky Outdoor photograph album, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Ohio Outdoor photograph album, 1974 (Box 8)